Contact

254-534-2005 (Mobile)

www.linkedin.com/in/ ambergarretsonaprn (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Nursing
Healthcare Management
Program Development

Certifications

Clinical Nurse Specialist; Wellness through Acute Care (Adult-Gerontology) (ACCNS-AG)

Acute/Critical Care Nurse - Adult (CCRN)

Amber Garretson

Intensive Care Clinical Nurse Specialist at OU Medicine, Inc. Oklahoma City Metropolitan Area

Summary

Accomplished leader with multiple records of achievement in nursing combined with successes in building a hospital and clinic program from the ground up. Experience encompasses delivering quality, patient-centered care, with specialized skills in Medical Intensive Care, Emergency Medicine, and Home Health. Strong capacity to lead teams and collaborate with clinicians to devise and develop care plans, order sets, clinical pathways, and best practices. Demonstrated ability to consistently monitor regulatory procedures to ensure standards and guidelines are met and surpassed. Talented educator recognized for guiding, mentoring and training student nurses and new graduates. Offers additional transferable skills in strategic planning, communication methodologies and data/database analysis gleaned from experience working in U.S. healthcare markets.

Experience

OU Medicine, Inc.

Intensive Care Clinical Nurse Specialist: Sepsis, MICU, RRT May 2018 - Present (2 years 4 months)

Oklahoma City, Oklahoma Area

- -Optimizes patient care by working with staff, management and administration.
- •This includes evaluating current practices; reviewing organizational policies and procedures; creating, implementing and evaluating clinical pathways; serving on or leading committees; participating in shared governance.
- -Facilitator and resource for the healthcare system.
- -Sepsis APRN for the hospital: Receives sepsis pages from ED; rounds on patient and reviews EMR for bundle compliance.
- -ERNT: Covers for Rapid Response Team.

University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center Adjunct Faculty August 2018 - Present (2 years 1 month)

Oklahoma City, OK, United States

Alliance Health Deaconess Emergency Room Charge Nurse October 2017 - April 2018 (7 months)

Oklahoma City, Oklahoma Area

- -Under the general supervision of the ER Manager, the ER Charge Nurse is responsible for assisting the Manager in providing nursing leadership to the nursing unit.
- -Provides feedback to the Supervisor regarding patient care, budgetary, and strategic planning opportunities for improvement.
- -Demonstrates an advanced level of clinical skills and the ability to support others to achieve the delivery of quality care.
- -Participated in QI projects:

Began work on Emergency Department Surge Plan.

University of Oklahoma
Bariatric Program Manager
February 2017 - October 2017 (9 months)

Oklahoma City, Oklahoma Area

- -Worked closely with Surgeon, Nurse Practitioner, dietitians, physical therapists, behavioral health specialists, and billing/insurance administrators to coordinate bariatric patient's care plan.
- -Created Bariatric Clinical Pathway.
- -Created educational material to be provided and taught to nurses, and ancillary staff, in order for facility to gain accreditation.
- -Performed weekly Bariatric Information Seminars for patients interested in bariatric surgery.
- -Created presentation for above mentioned information seminars.

-Participate in GI Lab specific initiatives and process improvement.

Oklahoma City V A Medical Ctr GI Lab RN May 2016 - February 2017 (10 months) Oklahoma City, Oklahoma Area

- -Supervise new employees, patient care assistant, vocational nurses, student nurses.
- -Educate patient and family in endoscopy.

Central Texas Veterans Healthcare System Nursing Supervisor October 2014 - May 2016 (1 year 8 months)

Killeen/Temple, Texas Area

- -Designated authority, responsibility, and accountability for managing and directing nursing employees and staffing units.
- -Was responsible for allocating resources as necessary during the nonadministrative tours of duty due to tour-to-tour unplanned leave or changes in patient acuity, or emergency situations and disasters.
- -Played a key role in the ongoing systematic evaluation and improvement of the quality and effectiveness of nursing care and services as they affect patient outcomes.
- -Frequently rounded to evaluate patient care.
- -Assisted the Nurse Managers by contributing to performance evaluations, educational development for the non-administrative tour employees, and meeting performance measures.
- -Was a consultant to physicians in patient care and resource/discharge planning.

MGA Home Healthcare Branch Director January 2014 - October 2014 (10 months)

Austin, Texas Area

- -Was responsible for admissions and re-certification assessments; including supporting documentation, as assigned.
- -Was responsible for maintaining compliance with all reimbursement guidelines.
- -Participated in program development and implementation.
- -Supervised field nurses who work in pediatric patient's homes.
- -Maintained communication with external case managers (State-funded programs, Medicaid/DDD, and third party payers), clinical updates and continuing authorizations and re-verification of eligibility.
- -Reviewed admissions and follow-up documentation within established time frames. (24 hours for initial paperwork and 48 hours for follow-up visits).
- -Created orientation materials for General Nursing Orientation.
- -Performed continuing education for field staff members which included: tracheostomy, ventilator and feeding tube classes.

Girling Health Care
Field RN
October 2012 - January 2014 (1 year 4 months)
Temple, Texas

-Offered emotional support to client and facilitated educational goals

- -Experienced with many styles of modified/customized assisted devices, i.e., standing devices, sitting apparatuses, wheelchair, Hoyer lift, and AFO's (leg braces). Reinforced physical therapy exercises daily with use of equipment like wedges and bolsters.
- -Educated patients and families regarding importance of health promotion and disease prevention.

Seton Medical Center Harker Heights Staff Nurse - Emergency Department/ICU May 2012 - January 2014 (1 year 9 months) Harker Heights, TX

Seton Medical Center located in Harker Heights, TX is an 83-bed acute care facility with a 17-bed ER and 12-bed ICU. As a Staff Nurse in the ER and ICU, I:

- -Was an active member of chest pain committee.
- -Was a member of the Rapid Response Team.
- -Cared for patients with various medical disorders with the emphasis of patients with sepsis, GI bleeds, DKA, MODS, ARDS, and ARF.
- -Floated to step-down, telemetry, and med-surg floors, as needed.

Scott & White Healthcare
Staff Nurse - Emergency Department/MICU
May 2011 - May 2013 (2 years 1 month)
Temple, TX

Scott & White Hospital, now Baylor Scott & White, is a Level I Trauma Center with a 40-bed Medical ICU and a 46-bed ER. As a Staff Nurse in the ER and MICU, I cared for patients with various types of multi-system failure patients with an emphasis on medical trauma and various closed injuries at the ratio of 3:1 in the MICU and 4:1 in the ER.

- -Was a member of the Rapid Response Team.
- -Cared for patients with various medical disorders with the emphasis of patients with sepsis, GI bleeds, DKA, MODS, ARDS, and ARF.
- -Floated to step-down, telemetry, and med-surg floors, as needed.
- -Decisively and confidently made judgments on patient conditions based on vital signs, patient presentation, and initial assessment; triaged to appropriate zone; activated specialized team when indicated (cath lab, trauma team, rapid response stroke team, etc.)
- -Demonstrated exemplary documentation skills by accurately maintaining nurses' notes and promoting sufficient communication among care staff.

NEXTEL

Project Manager May 2005 - July 2009 (4 years 3 months)

Temple, Texas

Education

Oklahoma State University

Master's degree, Health/Health Care Administration/

Management · (2019 - 2022)

University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center Master's Degree, Clinical Nurse Specialist (2016 - 2019)

Grand Canyon University
Bachelor's degree, RN-BSN · (2011 - 2012)

Temple College

Associate of Arts and Sciences (A.A.S.), Registered Nursing/Registered Nurse · (2009 - 2011)